And so now the time has come to talk about the most crucial aspect of Rag, which is the idea of vectors.
이제 랙의 가장 중요한 측면에 대해 얘기할 때가 됐습니다 벡터 개념이죠
If you're already familiar with vectors and vector embeddings, hang on in there.
벡터와 벡터 내장법에 익숙하시다면 잠시만요
I'm going to go fairly quickly through this.
빨리 훑어보도록 하죠
You may pick up a thing that you didn't know about as I as I explained this.
몰랐던 걸 알게 될 수도 있어요 제가 설명한 대로요
So first of all, there's an important bit of background information, which is that we've been talking
먼저 중요한 배경 정보가 있습니다 이 과정을 통해 다양한
about a bunch of different LMS through this course, but almost all the LMS we've been talking about
LMS에 관해 얘기해왔는데요 우리가 얘기한 거의 모든 LMS는 하나의
have been one kind of LM called an autoregressive LM.
종류였습니다 자동적 허용 LM이라고 불리는 거죠
And there is, in fact a completely different category of LM known as Autoencoding.
LM에는 완전히 다른 범주가 있습니다 자동 코드화라고 하죠
So what's the difference?
차이가 뭐죠?
Autoregressive LMS or LMS, which are given a past set of tokens and they are required to generate the
LMS 자동 이탈 LMS는 과거의 토큰 세트를 받고 시퀀스에서 다음 토큰을 생성해야
next token in the sequence a future token given the past.
합니다 미래 토큰이요 과거가 주어지죠
And they keep doing that repeating creating the next token.
계속 반복해서 다음 토큰을 생성하죠
Given the history of tokens, that's an autoregressive LM.
토큰의 역사를 보면 자동적 차별적인 LM이에요
And of course it's all the rage.
물론 그게 대세죠
It's most of the ones that we work with.
우리가 함께 일하는 대부분의 사람들이죠
And of course it's it's GPT four and Claude and Gemini and so on.
GPT 4호와 클로드 제미니 계획도 있고요
There's also these types called autoencoding, and they take a full input that represents both the past
자동 코드 형식이라는 것도 있습니다 과거와 현재, 미래를 모두 나타내는 완전한
and the present and the future.
입력을 하죠
It's a full bit of input, and they create one output that reflects the whole input.
입력 비트가 가득하고 입력 전체를 반영하는 출력 비트를 생성하죠
And so to make that real, there's some obvious examples.
그걸 현실화하려면 몇 가지 확실한 예가 있죠
Sentiment analysis where you take in a sentence and say if it's positive or negative.
감정 분석은 문장을 보고 긍정인지 부정인지 판단하는 거예요
Classification where you take a sentence and put it into buckets.
분류 구역에서는 문장을 양동이에 담아 Put을 해요
Both things that we did actually explore briefly with the Huggingface pipelines a couple of weeks ago.
2주 전에 어깅페이스 파이프라인과 관련해 잠깐 탐구한 것들이죠
And those are both examples of Autoencoding llms.
둘 다 자동 코드 llms의 예죠
There is another way that they are used as well, and it is to create something called a vector embedding.
또 다른 방법으로 사용되기도 합니다 벡터 내장이라는 것을 생성할 때 사용되죠
And that's what we're going to be talking about today.
오늘 얘기할 게 바로 그거예요
So a vector embedding is a way of taking a sentence of text or a bunch of different things, but usually
벡터 엠베딩은 텍스트의 문장이나 다른 여러 가지를 취하는 방법인데 보통은 텍스트의
a sentence of text.
문장이죠
And turning that into a series of numbers, a series of numbers that in some way reflect the meaning
그걸 일련의 숫자로 바꾸는 거죠 어떤 면에선 그 텍스트의 의미를 반영하는
behind that text.
일련의 숫자요
And we'll go through exactly what that means in just a second.
그게 무슨 뜻인지 잠시 후에 살펴보죠
It sounds a bit abstract right now, but the idea is that take some text, convert it into numbers,
지금은 좀 추상적으로 들리지만 아이디어는 텍스트를 숫자로 변환하는 겁니다
and those numbers you could think of as representing a point in space.
그 숫자들은 공간의 한 점을 나타내는 비트죠
So if we took some text and we turned it into three numbers, you could think of that as being like
텍스트를 세 개의 숫자로 바꾼다고 해보죠 엑스나 Y, Z로
an X, Y, and z that would represent exactly where abouts something is located in space.
생각할 수 있어요 이건 공간에서 무언가가 있는 위치를 나타내죠
As it happens, usually when you do this, it gets converted into hundreds or thousands of numbers.
보통 이렇게 하면 수백, 수천 개의 숫자로 변환돼요
So it represents a point in like 1000 dimensional space.
천 차원 공간에 있는 한 지점을 나타내는 거예요
And that's kind of hard for us to visualize because we can only think in three dimensions, but it's
시각화하기가 좀 어렵죠 우린 3차원으로만 생각할 수 있으니까요 하지만
the same idea.
생각은 같죠
It's reflecting a point in space, and that point is meant to represent in some way the meaning behind
공간의 점을 반영하고 어떤 의미에서든 그 점은 자동 인코딩의
the text that went in to generate that are examples of auto encoding.
예로 생성된 텍스트의 의미를 나타내죠
Llms are Bert from Google.
구글의 버트예요
You may remember we actually mentioned Bert right back, I think in the first week.
첫 주에 버트 얘기를 했던 거 기억하시죠?
Uh, so so Bert's been around for a while.
버트는 꽤 오래 출연했어요
Um, there's also open AI embeddings from OpenAI, and that's actually the auto autoencoder model that
OpenAI의 오픈 인공지능 엠베딩도 있는데 자동 오토 젠코더 모델로
we'll be using this week for our Rag projects.
이번 주에 래그 프로젝트에 사용할 거예요
So let me just talk a bit more about what we mean by meaning.
비트 코어의 의미에 대해 좀 더 얘기해 보죠
So first of all, you can use you can create one of these vectors for a single character, for a token
먼저, 여러분은 단일 문자에 대한 벡터 중 하나를 만들 수 있습니다 토큰이나 다수의 문자
or a bunch of characters, for a word, for a sentence, for a paragraph, for an entire document,
단어, 문장, 단락, 전체 문서에 대한 것 혹은 추상적인 것에
or even for something abstract.
대한 것에요
Like in my company, Nebula, we create vectors for things like talent and jobs and things like that.
제 회사, 네뷸라처럼 재능이나 일자리 같은 것의 벡터를 만들어요
Often when you're working with these vectors, they will have hundreds or even thousands of dimensions,
이런 벡터들을 작업할 때 수백, 수천 개의 차원이 있는 경우가 많아요
will be like a thousand numbers that represent this one block of text.
텍스트 한 덩어리를 나타내는 수천 개의 숫자처럼요
And now I've said a few times that these numbers reflect the meaning behind the inputs.
이 숫자들이 입력값의 의미를 반영한다고 여러 번 말씀드렸죠
What exactly does that mean?
그게 무슨 뜻이죠?
So to put simply, one of the things it means is that if you have a bunch of paragraphs of text that
간단히 말해서, 이 말은 여러 단락의 텍스트가 서로 가까운 공간의
all end up mapping to similar points in space that are close to each other.
비슷한 지점으로 매핑이 된다는 거죠.
That should mean that these blocks of text have similar meaning.
이 텍스트 블록들은 비슷한 의미를 가져야 해요
They don't necessarily need to contain the same words.
같은 단어를 쓸 필요는 없어요
They could be completely different words, but their meaning is the same.
완전히 다른 단어일 수도 있지만 의미는 같아요
They will be close to each other in vector space, so things close to each other in when they're turned
벡터 공간에서 서로 가까워질 거예요 숫자로 바뀔 때 서로 가까워진다는
into numbers should mean similar things.
건 비슷한 걸 의미하죠
And that's the basic idea behind this.
그게 기본 아이디어죠
There's also some more sophisticated ideas behind this, including this point that you can do what's
이 이면에는 좀 더 정교한 아이디어가 있어요 이 점을 포함해서요 이런 것들의
what's sometimes called vector math behind the meanings of these things.
의미 뒤에 숨은 벡터 수학이라고 불리는 걸 할 수 있어요
And there's this example that's very often given it's been around for a long time, this example.
그리고 이 예시가 있습니다. 아주 오래된 예시죠.
And you may well have heard of it before, and it says, supposing that you have the word king, and
들어 보셨을 수도 있는데 킹이라는 단어가 있다고 가정해 봅시다 킹이라는
you took the word king, and you used one of these vector encodings to find the the point in space that
단어를 가지고 벡터 인코딩을 이용해서 킹이라는 단어를 나타내는 공간의
represents the word king.
점을 찾는다고 해보죠
And you also find the vector that reflects the word man.
인간이란 단어를 반영하는 벡터도 찾을 수 있죠
And the vector that reflects the word woman.
여성이라는 단어를 반영하는 벡터도요
And you take the word king and you subtract man from it, which means you kind of move backwards in
킹이라는 단어에서 남자를 빼면 남자가 있는 방향으로
the direction of man and you add woman, which means that you move forwards in the direction of woman.
뒤로 가고 여자가 있는 방향으로 전진하는 거예요
What you've effectively done is you've taken the concept, the meaning of king, and you've said, I
당신은 왕이라는 개념을 받아들여서 남자를 여자로 대체하고
want to replace the man with woman in this meaning king.
싶다고 했어요 즉, 왕이라는 뜻이죠
And somewhat remarkably, if you do this, you do actually end up in the position in vector space,
그리고 놀랍게도 이렇게 하면 벡터 공간에 들어가게 됩니다 퀸이라는
which is the same position as the position for the word queen.
단어가 있는 위치와 같은 위치죠
So it really does seem that if you take the word king, the meaning of the word king, and you replace
그러니까 왕이라는 단어에서 왕의 의미를 따지고 남자 측면을 여자로
the man aspect of it with woman, you're then at something which reflects the meaning of the word queen.
대체하면 여왕이라는 단어의 의미를 반영하는 무언가가 되는 거죠
And so it's in that sense that these vectors really seem to reflect the meaning behind the words they
그런 점에서 벡터들은 벡터들이 나타내는 단어의 의미를 반영하는 것
represent, both in terms of similar words being close to each other and the ability to carry out this
같아요 비슷한 단어들이 서로 가까이 있다는 점과 벡터 수학을
kind of vector math that allows you to understand the relationship between concepts.
수행하는 능력도요 덕분에 개념 간의 관계를 이해할 수 있죠
So what's this got to do with rag?
이게 래그랑 무슨 상관이죠?
Here's where it all comes together.
여기서 모든 게 합쳐져요
This is the big idea behind Rag now.
래그의 핵심 아이디어죠
So this is the same diagram we had before.
아까와 같은 도표예요
But there's going to be a little bit more going on.
비트보다 더 많은 걸 할 거예요
At the top we've got a new box called encoding LM.
상단엔 LM 인코딩이라는 새 상자가 있죠
This is something which is able to take some text and turn it into a vector.
어떤 텍스트를 벡터로 바꿀 수 있는 거죠
And at the bottom we have something called a vector data store.
맨 밑에는 벡터 데이터 저장소가 있어요
It's like the data store we had before the knowledge base.
지식 기반 이전에 있던 데이터 저장소 같아요
But now along with text, we can also store the vector that represents that text, the vector that represents
텍스트와 함께 텍스트를 나타내는 벡터도 저장할 수 있어요 텍스트의 의미를
the meaning of that text.
나타내는 벡터요
All right.
좋아요
So here's what we do.
이렇게 하죠
In comes a question from the user.
사용자가 질문을 던지죠
The first thing we do is we take that question and we turn it into a vector sometimes called a vectorizing.
가장 먼저 할 일은 질문을 벡터로 바꾸는 겁니다 벡터화라고도 하죠
So supposing the question was who is Amy Me.
에이미 미가 누구냐는 질문이라면요
Lancaster.
랭커스터요
We take who is Amy Lancaster, and we turn that into a vector that reflects the meaning of the question,
에이미 랭커스터가 누구인지를 질문의 의미로 해석하는
Who is Amy Lancaster?
거예요
You can probably imagine what I'm going to say next.
제가 다음에 할 말은 아마 짐작이 가실 거예요
What we then do is we go to the vector database and we say, tell me what information is in this vector
이제 벡터 데이터베이스로 가서 벡터 데이터베이스에서 벡터들이 에이미 랭커스터에 가까운
database where the vectors are close to the vector for who is Amy Lancaster?
곳에 있는 정보를 요청합니다 에이미 랭커스터가 누구인가요?
So look at all the different documents we've got in there.
저 안에 있는 다양한 문서들을 보세요
We've turned them all into vectors.
전부 벡터로 만들었어요
Some of those vectors will be close to the question who is Amy Lancaster?
에이미 랭커스터가 누구인지 궁금해할 벡터들이 있을 거예요
Give me those vectors and give me the the original information, the text that was turned into those
벡터들을 제공하고 벡터로 바뀐 원래 정보와 텍스트를 제공하죠
And presumably it's extremely likely that the actual air document for Amy Lancaster is going to be located
에이미 랭커스터의 항공 문서가 벡터와 가까운 곳에 있을 가능성이 높습니다
somewhere close to the vector, who is Amy Lancaster?
에이미 랭커스터가 누구죠?
And so when we get that information, we quite simply take that text.
그래서 정보를 얻으면 텍스트를 get 하면 되죠
And just like before with the toy example, we shove that in the prompt to the LLM, we get back the
이전의 장난감 예제처럼 그걸 LLM 프롬프트에 밀어넣으면 응답을 얻습니다
response, presumably taking advantage of the extra context.
아마도 추가적인 컨텍스트를 이용하겠죠
And that's what goes back to the user.
그게 사용자에게 돌아가는 거죠
So it's just like the toy example, except we're using a much more powerful technique for looking up
장난감 예제와 같지만 관련 데이터를 찾는 데 훨씬 더 강력한 기술을
the relevant data, using vectors as a way of understanding which of our bits of knowledge have the
사용합니다 벡터를 이용해 우리의 지식 중 어떤 것이 질문의 의미와 가장
most similar meaning to the meaning of the question.
유사한지 이해하는 거죠
Well, that's really all there is to it.
그게 다인 것 같아요
And that's a wrap for this week, because it's next time that we're going to put this into action and
이번 주의 마무리가 되었네요. 왜냐하면 다음 시간에는 이것을 action에 넣고
actually see vectors in databases.
데이터베이스에서 벡터를 볼 것이기 때문이죠.
We're also next time going to start looking at something called Lang Chain, a wonderful, wonderful
다음엔 랭 체인이라는 것도 살펴볼 겁니다 프레임워크가 훌륭하죠
framework which is designed to make it easy to build these kinds of applications.
이런 응용 프로그램을 쉽게 만들도록 디자인됐어요
We could do it all the manual way.
전부 수동으로 할 수 있어요
We could actually create vectors and store them in vector databases using various APIs.
벡터를 생성해 다양한 API를 이용해 벡터 데이터베이스에 저장할 수 있죠
But Lang Chain makes it super simple, as you will see.
랑 체인은 아주 간단해요 곧 보시겠지만요
And it's going to be a bit like the Gradio experience, where in just a couple of lines of code, we're
그래디오 경험과 좀 비슷할 겁니다 코드 두어 줄로 아주
going to be doing very powerful things.
강력한 걸 하는 거죠
So I'm excited about it.
그래서 기대돼요
I hope you are too.
당신도 그랬으면 좋겠네요
And I'll see you then.
그때 봐요